We're going to take a bit of a mental break because we've
been doing a lot of JavaScripts,
doing a lot of the heavy lifting stuff.
Let's talk about styling your app because let's face it,
as web developers,
styling your app is a real thing.
Managing CSS, a lot of us might not love it.
I happen to love CSS,
but I wanted to show you what's possible with
view so that those ideas can get
flowing when it comes to time to style the app.
So I'm going to go ahead and go back to the playground,
run dev, and we good.
Okay. Let's take a look at our base counter
since this is what we have showing up on the screen right now.
Okay. So when we've talked a lot about templates,
we talked a lot about script, let's talk about style.
So actually, I take that back.
I'm going back to playground because this is
a simpler file to read right now.
Base counter has a lot of stuff going on.
So the style block here,
what exactly is going on here?
Well, let's start by doing something pretty simple.
Let's go ahead and just tag the entire page and just give it
a background color of say,
let's do the background color,
Paya whip, and I can't spell.
All right. That should do it.
Okay. This is great.
Now, what's going on here actually?
What's going on is that when you just have a standard style tag,
what view is doing is injecting
the style basically across the entire app.
So in other words, you see these buttons right here.
If I go ahead and did button border red,
or let's see 10px solid red like that,
you'll see that it impacts everything.
You might be thinking, oh,
is it because it's app.view?
It's no because the styles are being injected globally.
So any component that comes on
this page is going to get impacted by this.
So this is a double-edged sword like anything else.
There are times that you want CSS to cascade and do its thing.
A lot of times actually though,
you don't want it to do its thing.
You want your styles to be encapsulated
to the components you're using.
So for instance,
if we're looking at the user card in this case,
you might want the buttons here to have a very specific style.
In this case, let's say we wanted the buttons to be
border 10px solid green.
You'll notice that if we just use
standard tile tag as it happens to be,
it'll happen to override.
While you might try to think of a way to reason why this is happening,
trust me, when you have hundreds and thousands of components
injecting global styles,
you do not want to debug that.
So this is like the first style of styling your app,
which is you can just drop CSS,
it will render everywhere.
The one that's the most popular is something called scope styles.
If you've never heard of scope styles before,
there are basically a way to do exactly as
the naming convention sounds to scope your styles to a specific area.
So what is actually happening underneath the hood?
Because I talked a lot about
view building on what already exists in the ecosystem.
Well, scope CSS, what it's actually doing if we take a look here,
is it's actually taking a look at
the elements that are relevant to this particular component,
and it's appending a unique data attribute.
So you see here this data.v.b600,
that is what's basically being appended to the HTML.
Then what's cool about this is if you look at the console,
where's my CSS? Oh, it's down here, I hit it.
Look at this style.
It's button using the attribute selector to then go ahead and apply
those styles specifically within that context.
That actually works pretty well,
assuming that the rest of your global CSS
isn't written in a highly specific way.
This actually works really great,
and a lot of people have a lot of success using scope styles.
But scope styles isn't perfect because if we went ahead,
and I don't know, there's something a little bit more specific like this.
I think that didn't quite do it. It's fine.
I'll just do this. I'll just go the lazy route.
If someone somewhere in your Enterprise app decided to bang
port in the button, scope styles are not going to save you, by any means.
You're still going to have to be stuck with the cascade effect.
There's something to be said about being disciplined about writing your CSS,
so that could be something your team does.
But what if there was a better way?